<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Evan's research blog</title>
    <description>Blogging about stuff</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>M82 models</title>
        
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;At some point, I’ll fill in some of the backstory from the past three months. In the meantime,
here’s where things stand currently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have a working equilibrium model for the Milky Way with a hot, hydrostatic halo and a rotating disk in vertical hydrostatic equilibrium that is stable for a Gyr.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have a working equilibrium model for M82 with the same structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/M82-models/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/M82-models/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hydrostatic Blues</title>
        
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I described the analytic calculation I’m doing in order to set up a 3D 
disk in vertical hydrostatic equilibrium with my NFW + Miyamoto-Nagai profile. Here’s a density
projection of what the resulting disk looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/Hydrostatic-Blues/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/Hydrostatic-Blues/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Milky Way 3D</title>
        
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Once we add a third dimension, the initial conditions for an isothermal disk get a bit more complex.
In addition to balancing the radial components of the gravitational potential with circular velocity, 
I now need to balance the vertical acceleration via a pressure gradient, i.e. I need to make sure the 
disk is in hydrostatic balance. Given that the pressure and density can be related for an isothermal 
gas via the expression &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P = \rho c_{s}^{2}&lt;/script&gt;, this translates to calculating the vertical density profile 
at each radial location in the disk.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/Milky-Way-3D/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/Milky-Way-3D/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Milky Way 2D</title>
        
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;In order to simulate galaxy outflows, we need to start with reasonable approximation of a
gas disk that is stable over many rotation periods. This post begins what will be a series of 
tests describing the setup of such a disk. For simplicity, I’ll start with a two-dimensional simulation.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/Milky-Way-2D/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/Milky-Way-2D/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Keplerian Disk</title>
        
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;So we’ve seen how Cholla does with rotating flows in general, but how about the classic problem
of a disk in Keplerian rotation? Generally, there are two challenges in simulating such disks 
with a static grid code: first, the orbital speeds near the center of the disk can get extremely large
as the resolution of the simulation is increased, and second, advection errors (like those seen in the 
Gresho test) lead to artificial accretion through the disk.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/Keplerian-Disk/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/Keplerian-Disk/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Modified Gresho Test</title>
        
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;To test the 2D static potential in Cholla, I’ve created a modified version of the
Gresho vortex test that balances the centrifugal force created by the angular velocity
profile with an artificially added centripetal acceleration. The centripetal acceleration
is added in the same operator-split manner as the gravitational acceleration would be, 
so it is effectively a test of the 2D static potential in Cholla. This acceleration takes the 
form&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/Modified-Gresho-Test/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/Modified-Gresho-Test/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Moving Gresho Test</title>
        
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The moving Gresho vortex test is identical to the Gresho test describd in the 
previous post, except that the fluid is given a constant velocity boost
in the x-direction. Here, I apply a velocity boost of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_x = 1.0&lt;/script&gt; and show
the results at &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t = 3.0&lt;/script&gt;, after the vortex has moved across the domain three
times. I’m using periodic boundaries and a &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;40\times40&lt;/script&gt; cell grid.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/Moving-Gresho-Test/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/Moving-Gresho-Test/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gresho Test</title>
        
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The Gresho vortex test is a notoriously difficult problem for grid-based (and SPH) 
codes. A rotating vortex is initialized such that the centrifugal force is balanced 
by the pressure gradient. The solution is time-independent. For these tests, I used
the initial conditions described in Liska &amp;amp; Wendroff (2003).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/Gresho-Test/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/Gresho-Test/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gravity (Part 2)</title>
        
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to the operator-split source term update I added last week,&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/Gravity-Part-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/Gravity-Part-2/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gravity (Part 1)</title>
        
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;The time has come to implement a gravitational potential in &lt;em&gt;Cholla&lt;/em&gt;.
To do this, I’ll need to couple the gravitational source terms to the
momentum and energy equations:&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/Gravity-Part-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/Gravity-Part-1/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>